Guide to the Marcus G. Langseth Diaries
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Marcus G. Langseth Diaries
1955-1996
Langseth, Marcus G.
2.25 linear ft. (2 record cartons)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1588
9007821
Diaries of Marcus G. Langseth, a pioneer in marine geothermal research, researcher at the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, and professor of geology at Columbia University. The diaries include scientific observations and personal anecdotes.
History
A pioneer in marine geothermal research, Marcus Gerhardt Langseth was associated with the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory for most of his 40-year career. Beginning as a research assistant and graduate student in the mid-1950s, he became a senior research scientist and an adjunct professor of earth and environmental sciences at Columbia University.
Dr. Langseth was born in Lebanon, Tennessee, on Nov. 24, 1932 and received his bachelor's degree from Waynesburg College in 1954. He began working at the Lamont-Doherty observatory as a summer employee in 1953, and joined the staff full time in 1955. After a two-year stint in the Army from 1956-1958, he came back to Lamont as a research staff assistant and in 1959 he started to pursue graduate studies in geophysics at Columbia University and he earned his PhD from the University in 1964.
Dr. Langseth remained affiliated with Columbia University and the Lamont-Doherty Observatory throughout his career. He was an expert in heat flow studies, and much of his research involved collecting and analyzing data about the way that heat moves on the surface of the Earth. He developed instruments that Apollo crews used to study heat flow on the moon. This work earned him NASA's Special Achievement Award. In 1993, Dr. Langseth was appointed the Palisades Geophysical Institute Senior Scientist at Lamont.
Langseth died of lung cancer in 1997.
Scope and Content
The diaries include scientific observations and personal anecdotes. A typical journal may include meeting notes, scientific research observations, scientific calculations, drafts of correspondence or memos, and personal observations and anecdotes. Many journals include loose pages inserted into the notebooks with related or additional material.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 1 series
Series I: Diaries and Journals, 1955-1996
Subjects
Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory.; Langseth, Marcus G.; Geophysics--Observations.; Diaries.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Lillian Langseth Gift 09/12/2011 2011.2012.M053
[Provenance]
- Series I: Diaries and Journals, 1955-1996
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1955 February-May (Box 1)
  - 1960 May-1961 February (Box 1)
  - 1965 March-April (Box 1)
  - 1968 (Box 1)
  - 1968 December-1969 April (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1969 April- 1970 March (Box 1)
  - 1970 March-October (Box 1)
  - 1970 September- 1971 April (Box 1)
  - 1971 April- August (Box 1)
  - 1971 October-1972 March (Box 1)
  - 1972 March- 1973 May (Box 1)
  - 1973 January-February (Box 1)
  - 1973 November (Box 1)
  - 1974 (Box 1)
  - 1976 February- 1978 October (Box 1)
  - 1977 March- August (Box 1)
  - 1977 September-December (Box 1)
  - 1979 July (Box 1)
  - 1980 January (Box 2)
  - 1981 June- 1981 September (Box 2)
  - 1981 September- 1982 January (Box 2)
  - 1982 February- 1982 March (Box 2)
  - 1982 March- June (Box 2)
  - 1982 June- December (Box 2)
  - 1982 December- 1983 June (Box 2)
  - 1983 June- October (Box 2)
  - 1983 October - 1984 February (Box 2)
  - 1984 July- August (Box 2)
  - 1984 February- 1985 May (Box 2)
  - 1985 January- June (Box 2)
  - 1987 February- 1988 January (Box 2)
  - 1988 March- August (Box 2)
  - 1988 October- 1989 October (Box 2)
  - 1990 April-October (Box 2)
  - 1990 October- 1991 June (Box 2)
  - 1991 July- 1992 June (Box 2)
  - 1992 June- 1993 March (Box 2)
  - 1993 March- August (Box 2)
  - 1993 September- 1994 January (Box 2)
  - 1994 January - September (Box 2)
  - 1994 April- 1995 May (Box 2)
  - 1995 May- 1996 January (Box 2)
  - 1996 January- August (Box 2)
  - 1996 March-April (Box 2)
  - 1996 August-November (Box 2)